okay welcome everyone uh we are here we
are narrowing in on the 20th day we're
on day 19 of handmade hero the show
where we code an entire professional
quality game from scratch using nothing
no libraries uh no engine no nothing so
that we can learn about everything that
goes into a modern game uh and basically
the goal with this series is to show how
everything works uh so that everyone who
works on games will basically have a
richer understanding of what's involved
and they will always have the ability
not only to understand what their
engines or their libraries or whatever
is doing but also to drop down there and
fix problems create their own new
libraries uh improve upon the tech that
we have and basically just give everyone
the opportunity to understand the full
Pipeline and really be fully effective
and never let you know there be
limitations uh in their game development
because of the fact that something is
opaque to them and they don't have the
knowledge necessary to kind of go in
there and take charge of something
themselves I think has been going great
so far I've been overwhelmed uh by the
response from everyone I think it's
amazing and awesome and I can't thank
everyone enough uh for making the series
so exciting and so yeah with with that I
will simply say let's get to what we're
doing today which is finishing up uh the
win 32 platform layer today and tomorrow
I think will be the last days probably
that we'll be working on our win 32
platform layer uh and today what we want
to do is kind of work on our audio sync
uh explained yesterday the sorts of
stuff that we need to do for it and
today we're going to be trying to
actually get some of that stuff
implemented and hopefully test this a
little bit too just so we can have some
confidence that our frame Loop is
actually working properly uh before we
sort of push onwards now if you have
pre-ordered the uh the game uh on
handmad her.org you should have gotten a
link in your email where to a place
where you can download the source code
if you download that zip file that's up
there the source code it should have
everyday's uh source code in it so far
and what you want to do is since today
is day 19 if you want to follow along at
home you just unzip days 18 source and
that will line you up perfectly to what
we're about to do today so if you want
to follow along uh with this video and
code along at home just you understand
everything and try it out yourself uh
you can do that by just uh unzipping day
18 source that is what I will be
starting with right now uh all right so
what I'd like to do uh today
um is I just like to go ahead and talk a
little bit I I talked yesterday about
the the audio code I like to talk a
little bit about what I'm going to try
to do here uh because obviously uh it's
always a little confusing when we're
talking about some some of these
Concepts like audio sync and stuff
because it's really hard to see when I
draw the diagrams like I did yesterday
it's kind of clear what's going on at
least a little bit uh from the visuals
but you know when you look at code
there's an awful lot of code uh that you
write uh in the course thing this is you
know it's I don't know it's a thousand
lines of code and we've done a good job
keeping our platform layer simple
certainly uh so 1 thousand lines isn't
that much but even even just getting to
that point you start to see there's a
lot of uh stuff in here that's going on
and it can be a little confusing to tie
everything back uh to sort of a diagram
or to tie everything back to what we're
trying to do and so what I want to do is
kind of walk through it a little bit
here and just talk about what's not
happening now and what needs to happen
so that we can kind of maybe push
towards uh where we want to be again
we're not making our final platform
layer here so we don't have to get 100%
of the bugs out we don't have to get
100% of the perf out uh but we're trying
to set ourselves up so that it's a good
prototyping layer and we will our
prototypes built on this layer will be
roughly equivalent to what they will be
when we have the full uh full Power
Platform layer working so
basically what we know uh is we we are
going to open a sound buffer and we
talked about sound buffers extensively
early when we first implemented this
feature if you haven't watched those
videos I highly recommend you do it'll
kind of clarify to you what's going on
with direct sound when we output the
sound but basically what we are doing is
we're outputting 48,000 samples every
second to the sound card and what a
sample is is a sample is one value for
the left and one value for the right
channel that basically say the amplitude
at that one point in time uh so
basically what we're doing is we're
taking
48,000 amplitude points and that is
what's reconstructing the wave that's
coming out of the speakers uh to First
approximation there's a lot of stuff
that happens to it on its way out from
from you know the computer to the
speakers but you know to First
approximation that's basically what
we're doing is we're trying to find that
wave now for a number of reasons I
discussed ear um way back when we first
started doing this it's not strictly
possible to actually perfectly
synchronize those waves with what shows
up on the screen and the reason for that
is there can be delay uh that happens at
all different stages all the way out to
stuff that's completely external to the
computer for example if you have a HDMI
cable and even if we ensure that our
audio and video are synced perfectly
going out of the HDMI cable that may go
into a user's uh receiver where it gets
split off into like one thing that goes
out to speakers and one thing that goes
out to the TV for the video and those
might be delayed separately due to
circuitry and all sorts of other stuff
uh so to a large extent perfect sync is
not AI able on Modern Hardware I wish it
was it's not um so what we're trying to
do is not really achieve perfect sync
but what we are trying to do is make
sure that we don't do such a poor job in
our own uh outputting that basically we
we create a a really bad sync problem
even before the harbor gets we don't
want to exacerbate an already bad
situation by ourselves making a very
laggy uh LAX output of audio and video
so what we're trying to do is ensure
that as we output those
samples we try to have some measure of
control over when they are going out and
we hope that they are leaving they're
basically getting pushed out of the
computer we kind of want them to get
pushed out across the time period that
corresponds to the frame that we wanted
them to be heard with so if we want a
certain set of sounds to be heard uh
across the length of a particular frame
that we're outputting we're trying to
line it up so that they come out the
computer at that
time so we have very unfortunately we
have very limited uh ability to do this
uh on some platforms on some platforms
we have more but we have very limited
ability on some platforms on on Windows
Direct sound in particular which is what
we're using basically what we have to do
is the we have to use this thing called
get current position and what get
current position does is it allows us to
retrieve from direct sound where direct
sound believes uh the audio to be
playing at the time so it's where it's
sort of telling us this is where I think
uh the audio is playing out the hardware
at the moment and it returns us
something called the play cursor uh
which says what that is so what i' like
to do sort of at the beginning here is
just I'm going to go ahead and make a
debug diagram just using win32 uh as we
debug the win32 platform layer here I'm
going to make a little debug diagram
that draws the play cursor for us just
so we can sort of get a feel uh for
where it actually is in our rolling
sound buffer if that makes sense uh so
what I want to do here is basically
right at the end uh we're going to do a
thing here this win32 uh display buffer
in window sort of thing uh basically
what I'd like to do is start to think
about exactly um excuse me I'd like to
sort of try to get if you will exactly
where Windows says that play cursor is
at the time when we're about to do our
blit right so it's a little sloppy
because our blit isn't instantaneous but
you know we're going to try here so
basically what I'm going to do is I'm
just going to do a little thing here and
say you know no uh this is debug code so
we can probably do a thing here where
we're doing um I can't remember what our
uh what our definition was we had a
definition for it here uh code build.bat
uh we were going to
use uh
handmade internal uh so with handmade
internal uh we could go ahead here and
do this this sort of check so if this is
a if this is an internal build I'm going
to go ahead and ask that uh that buffer
for the play cursor uh basically
um right here and I'm going to wrap this
just because this is internal thing I'm
going to wrap it in some uh in some
braces here just so these two things
don't escape so it's just a little local
thing uh that I'm going to do here right
like this uh so what I'm going to do is
I'm going to ask it for where that play
cursor is and then I'm going to store
that
value so that on the next time around
when I draw the frame I'm going to
actually draw where we thought the play
cursor was relative to our buffer uh at
that time right so basically what I'm
going to do here is I'm going to say all
right I'm going to get that play cursor
and then I'm going to have a thing that
I'll put kind of up here just just a
variable it's not a global variable but
it's going to sort of be effectively
Global because it's in the scope here
I'm basically going to say all right um
you know once we actually get this thing
going and we're going to start this I'm
going to do a thing called uh debug last
play cursor and I'm just going to
remember uh basically where that debug
last play cursor was uh all the time so
we're basically going to say we get the
play cursor back I'm going to going to
set it uh like that and we don't
actually care if this call fails or
anything this is just debug code so we
don't have to check anything but we're
just going to take a look uh at where it
was and you know in in the uh at the
time when we're about to do our page
flip basically uh and you know what we
could do that even a little bit uh we
could do that even a little bit more uh
sort of
um sort of accurately I think by doing
it after the page flip is done so we'll
do it here right so that basically says
okay after the after we've submitted all
our stuff to GDI we don't really know
when GDI is going to display it yet
later on we'll sort of have more of a
ability to do that but I wanted to show
you how to do this code um you know just
get this code in there first and then
later when we have a lower latency page
flip where we can actually think about
it maybe a little bit more uh we can
sort of get this tighter but basically I
just want some semblance of a debug
display something that tells us roughly
where the audio was uh at the time when
we tried to do our page flip but I just
want to impress upon you that again
we're not getting 100% accurate stuff
out here Windows is taking that uh bit
map that we gave it and it's going to
possibly delay until the vertical
retrace to retrace to flip it so we're
just trying to get like within a 60th of
a second or something of the correct
answer just so we can see if we're
totally off base when we start to do our
audio sync so we're trying to get just
something so there we go I've got that
debug last play cursor and then what I'm
going to do is right here uh when we do
this win 32 display buffer and window
thing uh right before that happens
basically what I'm going to do is I'm
going to insert uh another call here
that's that's um going to call up in the
case where uh we're in the internal mode
I'm going to call a win32 debug uh sync
display or something like this right and
that's basically going to pass that that
Global back buffer uh and it's going to
pass whatever the last play cursor was
right that debug last play cursor so
that's that's all I'm going to do and
then I'm going to draw that on the
screen and I would like to also pass it
The Sound buffer if possible um
which let's see just so it can
understand sort of the length of the
sound buffer how big it is that sort of
thing so we have a thing here win32
sound output so I'm going to go ahead
and pass that as well so that's going to
take this thing here right so there we
go sound output uh and that's address
there so I'm going to go up to uh the
code up here and just drop that in here
is our internal uh debug function here
that's going to draw some stuff
hopefully we hope that it's going to
draw some stuff
uh and that's going to take this win32
sound output buffer uh first of all and
it's going to also take this offscreen
buffer uh and then it also has this this
dword here that is whatever the uh the
last play cursor was so that's the
that's where we thought the play cursor
was and then all I'm going to do uh
nothing particularly interesting all I'm
going to do is I'm going to pretend that
the width of the offscreen buffer
right maps to our entire sound buffer
right and uh you know what I'd also like
to pass if possible is I'd like to pass
our Target uh Hertz as well uh where is
that that's the game update Hertz there
we
go well seconds per frame is probably
better so let's pass that so I'm also
going to take the seconds per frame
there that's all I really wanted so what
I'm going to do is I'm going to
basically start by just drawing a really
simple excuse me couple things in here
I'm just going to draw basically maybe
some little uh rectangles that will sort
of demarcate where our uh desired frame
boundaries are if if that makes any
sense or S sorry rather where our our
page flips are and come to think of it
I'm probably going to want to draw more
of them than just the last one as well
so in some sense I think I may want to
basically do something where uh where we
actually have uh more of them kind of
here than than than just one so what I
think I might do um is go ahead and say
all right uh the debug last play cursor
actually we keep some number of them
right we keep some relatively large
number of play cursors and let's say
that we keep like say the
last let's say let's say if we're doing
it at 30 frames a second uh let's say we
keep the last 30 right so basically our
game update Hurtz uh we'll keep that
many of them if that makes sense okay uh
so we're basically going to to track
that many and the way that I'm going to
do that is just say uh that there's an
index into that array right uh and that
index I'm just going to update over time
so that we write in the last play cursor
uh based on on that piece of information
so uh here we go let's go ahead and do
that I'm going to do that here and we'll
expand this I think in a second here I I
feel like probably uh but for now right
uh so we'll basically just do that we'll
write in what the play cursor was into
the array and then if we happen to get
uh to the point where this is higher
than the array count we're just going to
wrap so it's just going to be we're
basically just going to be a circular
buffer where we just keep writing into
it and when we get to the very end we'll
go back to the beginning if that makes
sense so so that's it nothing
particularly fancy there that's all
we're doing hopefully that makes some
sense right um excuse
me uh why didn't that one to initialize
for us is that better expected constant
expression oh right sorry this uh this
game update hurts here has to actually
be something that can be a constant
expression so we can do that temporarily
there we
go all
right and uh let's see what else we got
wi 3db sync display that needs to take
uh our other parameter there the seconds
what was it actually called Target
seconds per frame so I'm going to pass
that as well and there we go let's see
screen buffer canot put one to addressa
what did I do did I forget the pointer I
did yes there we go these are supposed
to be pointers not
ampersands okay uh so now we just have
to do a thing where we're actually going
to pass uh this thing and how big it is
so we just need to pass uh basically our
our last play cursor array if that makes
sense so we're going to pass the whole
thing let's see there uh and then we
will just modify this uh to take that as
a pointer last play uh cursor count so
there we go all right uh so that's just
going to give us basically what we need
to draw uh and now what I need to do is
I need to step through that I need to do
play cursor index I need to step through
that array and I need to draw each one
of those into the um into the window
basically uh as as a little rectangle or
something so that we can actually see uh
what what is going on right ex me so uh
basically we got uh this this bit map
here we know that it is uh we know that
it is width wide right so we know that
this is how big it is and then we know
that we've got essentially our sound
buffer uh is going to have a thing that
has this uh secondary buffer size
divided by bytes per sample that's how
many sample indexes there are in the
entire buffer right um and this this guy
well I guess we don't actually care
because these play cursors are not
actually in samples they're in bytes uh
so basically we just need to use this
right the secondary buffer size is the
width we want to draw we we wish we had
a buffer that was that big to draw into
because that's the sort of range that
we're talking about but we actually only
have something that's this big uh which
means that we essentially have uh to
sort of map that secondary buffer size
range uh into the width that we have
right and so basically what we're going
to end up with is we're going to end up
with a a division here right we're going
to have um a a coefficient which is
basically going to say uh for something
that want that is actually mapped in the
buffer size uh and we want it to now be
mapped in the width uh we're going to
basically just make the ratio that Maps
those out and again if you remember I
talked about dimensional analysis before
this is ex exactly what what I'm doing
here I'm basically going to multiply
this coefficient uh by the input uh bite
count that we get from the from the play
cursor right those play cursors uh the
play cursors are in are in Sample buffer
bites uh and this is sample buffer btes
whereas I want them in pixels and this
is in pixels so I'm multiplying by
pixels dividing by sample buffer byes
the sample buffer byes units cancel and
I just get back uh basically the the
units that I wanted which is the the
pixel so I can draw it uh so that's all
that's going on here we talked about how
this worked uh previous streams when
we're talking about dimensional analysis
and ratios but that's exactly what all
that's doing right so what I want to do
is I want to draw this so basically I
can just say uh whatever the this the
value of last play cursor is in this
particular circumstance right uh
basically all I'm going to do is do a
floating Point multiply there uh to get
out basically uh what the x value is and
that is the x value for where that page
flip uh basically occurred now what I
want to do is I don't want it to go all
the way to the end of the buffer uh so
what I might do is also say okay you
know there's a little bit of pad here uh
let's say there's um you know um pad X
right so maybe we'll start 16 pixels
from the left and and uh 16 pixels from
the right just so it's so we can
actually see it so there's a little bit
of a margin there uh so what I'm going
to do is say that I want it to map to
actually a range that's not quite that
right I want to subtract that out of the
range uh and then when I actually draw
this x value I actually want it to be uh
looking more like that
right hopefully that makes some sense
and really I guess I'm going to have to
make this be an integer because these
are plotted as integers so we'll do the
multiplication first but then we're
going to have to actually convert it
back the reason I'm doing the
multiplication here is because I don't
want to have to do the multiplication in
in something uh hairy I want to be able
to store ratios and stuff like that so
I'm doing the multiplication in floats
and then I'm casting back to integers
when we need to draw so what I want to
do here is I want to do a little uh
debug draw line basically uh to draw uh
in fact I don't even need to draw a line
I can just draw a vertical um you know
like a hash basically which is extremely
simple to draw and I don't have to talk
about how to do something like you know
a crazy like bran hand line drawing or
something like this uh so what I'm going
to do is I'm just going to pass that in
I'm going to set the global back buffer
and then I'm just going to say you know
basically what I want that hash mark uh
where I want the top and bottom of it to
be so basically I'm going to say um you
know I don't know um Global back buffer
you know I guess I'll just do top and
bottom something like that and then
we'll just say what those are top is
going to be equal to something bottom is
going to be equal to something they will
basically be the global black back
buffer uh height you know I don't know
uh minus uh pad y let say and we'll make
that be 64 or something well we just
make it even board all the way around
this is going to be a very funny looking
diagram because it's going to be so tall
but hey what are you going to do we can
adjust that later uh and then I'm going
to say uh that it's just going to be a
pad y here oops that's that's broken pad
Y for the top and minus pad Y for the
bottom so then I'm just going to have to
write this function right which is a a
thing that draws a vertical uh line
which is extremely simple to do um
although you know whenever you're
writing stuff at a little level like
this it's always error prone it's why
you typically make a graphics Library we
don't quite have time to do that yet
that's what we will be doing sort of
next week and going forwards in our game
so that we'll just be able to call
things like draw a line and they'll just
work uh but for the time being it's
pretty simple for us to just sort of
hack something together uh that will
serve for our debugging purposes just
fine so uh what I'm going to do here is
I'm just going to step the Y this is
going to be the world's slowest and
worst uh way of doing this but I'm just
going basically step the line uh from
the top to the bottom basically uh and
then I will draw each pixel uh so really
all I need to do here is uh get a
pointer to the memory uh that we want
which is basically going to be
uh a cast of this uh let's see here a
cast of uh the memory for the bit map
which we've allocated and we've drawn to
this before so you guys are all familiar
with what I'm doing here but basically
this is the pixel that we're looking at
it's going to be that back buffer memory
uh times we're we're basically going to
move over however many bits per pixel it
is right which we already know exactly
how many uh it is uh it's basically four
bits per pixel you know I I don't know
why we didn't oh because it's in info
that's why I believe the bit map info is
the thing that stores the bits for Pixel
right but anyway I I feel like we should
have had bits for Pixel out here and I
feel like we didn't I feel like that got
removed or something I'm just going to
say bytes per pixel here I guess because
we already know what it is as well so it
could pretty much just be a pound to F
but anyway uh I'm going to move over the
X uh X bytes per pixel and that puts me
at the correct place but I also have to
put over go down y times the pitch uh
right cuz I have to go that far down
from the top of the buffer uh so we just
need to know what this actually is so
I'm going to I'm going to actually say
let's go ahead and get that back in
there I don't know why that went away um
I'm sure we could go back on the stream
historically and find out why it went
away maybe someone recommended it maybe
I was stupid one or the other uh both of
them are very possible but then when we
get to this uh particular pixel here
we're going to
write excuse me uh we're going to write
into it as a u32 uh so we can actually I
guess I can just cast un32 there so
we'll basically do it like this un32
star pixel we'll write to it uh and then
we will add to it uh the pitch again
right so there we
go that uh and when we write to the
pixel I don't know what we're going to
write in here we didn't actually specify
color I suppose we should allow the
person passing it in to specify color so
there we go uh and then we will just
have the draw vertical guy specify a
color and the color for now can just be
that color and now we just got to do
that bytes per pixel uh and fix the
errors I don't actually know again I
don't know why we got rid of bytes per
pixel it feels kind of weird that we did
but let's put it back in there bytes per
pixel uh and then when we are setting up
that pitch I would like to set up that
bytes per pixel so what I'd like to do
here is just say all right bytes per
pixel is here let's just go ahead and
get that in there so that we already
know uh because we've already got it
defined here and let's just do that oops
there we go just to make sure everyone's
using it just seems like a better idea
all right uh so why oh right it's top
not y it is top there we go and
secondary buffer size is something that
is passed in the sound output so that
actually needs to be referenced here all
right so we just typed in a crap on a
code there's probably some problems in
there but hopefully you understand what
I'm doing uh really all I'm doing is I'm
stepping through a bunch of cursor
positions that we saved in a rolling
buffer and I'm trying to draw them out
uh basically when I draw them out I am
going to have a um excuse me I'm going
to have a vertical line so all I did
there was I just stepped my pixel
pointer uh to the top I I stepped it
over by the X amount uh for each bite
per pixel and then I stepped it down by
the pitch however many the top was then
I just did as many rows as there were
between top and bottom and each time I
wrote the color out to the pixel I'm at
and advanced by the pitch to move down
to the next row really pretty basic uh
nothing interesting going on there at
all um like I said just kind of finicky
because we don't have a graphics library
at this point because we haven't gotten
to that point yet it's it's always hard
when you start from scratch you kind of
got to juggle as you kind of go upwards
but eventually and it's not that long
into it um you kind of get to a point
where you've got sort of a lot of
Leverage underneath you and then these
sorts of things aren't an issue anymore
because you've got your line draw you've
got your rectangle and you're you know
you're totally good to go um that's
exactly what I thought would happen you
always crash the first time because you
forget something uh so let's take a look
here at what we're doing uh
so um what do what are we doing wrong
our back buffer memory uh times the
bytes per pixel we did cast to un8 so
that's good our tap value of 16 times
the pitch and I don't actually know what
the pitch is the pitch may be negative
in this particular case I'd like to take
a look at that just to see uh Global
back buffer there we go take a look at
that the pitch is not so we're moving
forwards each time uh by that pitch
excuse
me so and then we've got a 704 what is
our Y at at this point it's at 123 so we
started off okay and then when we got to
123 uh we crashed which suggests that we
are advancing uh too far uh each time
through or something similar to this
that's a little suspicious and I'm not
sure why uh that would be the case so
let's take a good look here uh and see
uh what's actually going on so the
global back buffer memory pointer is
here right that's that's what that is
and our pixel pointer uh so I'm just I'm
just going to take a look at what uh our
pixel pointer is subtracted from that um
oh sorry let's take Let's Take This
Global back buffer uh I want to see what
the memory size is if that assuming that
that was a carar so we'll cast that and
see um oops unsigned carar sorry okay
okay sign carear uh so that is the
difference there so the pixel pointer
that's that's not good at all that is
not good at all what what did I do I did
something totally crazy there this is
one of those things where hey it's just
like I probably wasn't paying attention
and people on stream probably already
have it but I'm not going to look over
there uh again because I would like to
figure out uh I would like to go through
the steps that I would normally go
through uh to figure it out like I've
said many times on the stream I want to
kind of show how to debug stuff and so
when I have a bug I'd rather just kind
of go through it slowly on my own even
though people who have kind of been
watching and not talking the whole time
probably already can see what it is if
they're professionals um okay so
basically I know that I was going to
draw in this code right uh so let me
step in here and uh and and just start
going through it uh basically I've got
uh the global back buffer memory pointer
I know what that is and now I also know
what my pixel pointer is you can BAS see
U it here and it looks to me um oh I'm
just doing the subtraction backwards
that's that's that's it so that wasn't
actually wrong there we go uh so if I do
the subtraction here now again then then
I can actually see uh this is how far in
I stepped uh just from the just from the
beginning right so just that first step
when I did my pixel uh offset right when
I when I tried to start from the
beginning of the bitmap memory and uh go
a little bit further into it uh
basically all I was doing was I was
going to add this much which should be
let's let's double check the math here I
was going to add this much to get us to
the right row right which is
8190 uh and I was going to add uh this
much here uh for the X which which
should be the remainder right uh oops
inserted an errant token there right and
that looks right like it did the math
right now
5120 uh per row does that sound about
right 1280 * 4 that is what that is uh
and if if we were going to do 16 of
those right that is what we expect so
that looks like the right number of
bytes to step uh for the start in my
opinion that looks correct to me that is
what I would have expected uh to have
happen certainly so it looks like our
our
um our computation there is correct uh
then we come in here for our y our Y is
going to start at 16 it's going to step
to 704 and basically what we're saying
here is we're going to write to this
pixel location uh I want to you know
what I'm I'm I shouldn't have deleted
that I want to keep this uh here for now
so I can see what my offset is uh let's
see here Global offset memory so that I
can keep subtracting the two of those
and just see what their value is so
there we go
8194 uh and then I come through here uh
and do my addition and I step a row so
that is what I would expect to see
happen so I'm going to set a breakpoint
here and just make sure that this
happens okay that's interesting so it
actually succeeded uh the first time
through so it looks like it may be a
computation of our X that is wrong
perhaps our X is actually off this this
this computation here uh when I kind of
hastily sketched in this thing here it
looks like that might actually be wrong
because it looks like as long as the x
is low uh which it is at this point in
time uh the thing seems to work uh which
which would suggest that perhaps my ex
computation was incorrect so let's take
a look uh when I actually get the crash
now I'm just going to step directly to
the crash
what the actual x value is to see if
that's yeah
okay what do you that that is not a very
good x value okay uh I'm kind of glad
this is exactly what I hope to show on
the stream I know it seems weird to be
happy about showing you not being a very
good programmer but this is exactly what
I want to show on the stream uh is this
sort of thing because this sort of thing
happens to me all the time I am not a
great programmer at just writing exact
stuff right the first time always make
mistakes and then I just have to debug
them and it's really not a big deal it's
one of the reasons that you make
libraries as well is to kind of debug
them once and then have them and I I'm a
big advocate of that because I do make a
lot of caros mistakes um but yeah so I
just want to show you so you saw how I
found that right like that was pretty
clear how I went about debugging that I
just looked at what the memory was doing
I just looked at the pointers and I was
like oh okay I can see that it appears
to be tracking the Y properly so and on
an on an X that's reasonable it seemed
to work reasonably so I'm like I I guess
the only other parameter that is that
the X the X must be out of bounds uh and
then that kind of clued me into bother
looking at that now if I looked at the X
first originally I would have seen that
right away but I didn't do that uh so
maybe that's also a good thing to
remember always check all your
parameters once just to see um but yeah
so that's pretty simple we found the bug
there so it's just a bug in the X
computation which makes sense because I
just kind of slammed that in there and
didn't even think about it uh that was
that was not particularly uh
particularly bright certainly uh so
let's think about this a second what
were we actually doing uh so basically
what what I wanted to do with my
computation here and we'll go ahead and
and build that and then step in what I
was trying to do with this computation
here was just map uh from uh the the the
bites that the play cursor uh had
basically out to the the pixel with uh
and so I was hoping that this would be a
relatively straightforward thing but it
looks like uh I made a mistake when I
was doing that so what I'd like to do
here is I want to just so we can debug
this and look at it a little clearer
what I'd like to do is break the comput
into two steps so here is going to be
the two steps first I'm going to compute
um the the X in Real 32 right and then
I'm going to cast it and add the pad so
that way we can see the result of
multiplying by our coefficient and
hopefully that will let it inspect it a
little bit easier furthermore I'm going
to get this out into a local variable
and this is basically just me setting
myself up for debugging success I'm
basically just trying to get these
values out there uh so that you can see
uh exactly what is um uh what is going
on in the actual debugger right so I
just want to make sure I I compiled that
there there we go uh so uh in here we
can see what we get now in the watch
window and I can I can kind of very
easily uh make sure that the various
stuff that happens is uh reasonable so
um let's take a look there at that's a
totally reasonable value and so is the x
that results from it our coefficient
also seems reasonable able uh so let's
see what happens uh when we sort of go
through these here does it seem to do
anything particularly odd okay that is
really bizarre that looks like a totally
uh yeah so that looks like a totally
uninitialized value of some kind uh
which makes me think that our clearing
of the this buffer did not work properly
that is what I am thinking so I'm going
to check that but what I want to do as
well is also drop an assertion in here
because the other thing that uh we kind
of know is supposed to be true is that
this play cursor is always supposed to
be smaller than the secondary buffer
size that's just what we were expecting
to be true right uh you're never
supposed to be able to get um what is
this signed unsigned Mis mismatch uh
secondary buffer size I guess is an INT
so that's actually supposed to be a
dword I assume uh but I'm not sure if we
want to do it that way or not we can do
it that way for now all right uh so I'm
assuming that assert will now just fire
and that assert will basically tell us
uh that hey you're getting values that
are totally out of range for what you
were supposed to be allowing in this
particular function uh and I just wanted
to put that assertion in there so that
it's there and we'll catch those bugs in
the future probably shouldn't have put
one in there to begin with but was not
thinking all right so what that suggests
to me is perhaps that this is
uninitialized properly our our um our uh
buffer that I said was going to handle
like sort of the circular buffer there
uh so that was this right here and I
want to oh we we well that's the problem
it looks like when I was hastily typing
that in uh when I modified it to be uh
game update Hertz I uh I accidentally
deleted the thing I had so carefully uh
included you'll notice last night in
John's um language demonstration he did
the initialized by default unless you
asked for it not to be thing I would
love that feature so much CU most of the
time I want things cleared to zero uh
and stuff like that where you just you
accidentally delete it is just it makes
you prone to errors that you shouldn't
have uh so there we go all right so
we're totally set now for drawing uh
that's obviously drawing our stuff the
way we wanted it to draw uh
unfortunately we also have the problem
uh of basically it looks like there's a
little bit more than uh 30 of them is
more than actually fits so I'm going to
maybe do a little less than that I'll do
half that just so it stays on the page
so there we
go yeah that looks about right so
basically we can see already from this
uh is we do have problems with our
timing already you can kind of see just
from what I'm looking at here you can
see they're not equally spaced uh that
actually reminds me of something I was
thinking about last night uh after we
had finished the stream that I
remembered there was a a thing that we
had done wrong that I forgot
about basically what I was remembering
was uh we did our um and anyway we'll we
will go right back to the audio thing in
a minute but I this reminded me of this
and we should we should fix it while
we're here since we're doing the exactly
this sort of stuff and this says not
tested yet probably buggy which is true
uh basically the timing stuff here I was
doing a little thing here to sort of
lock our frame rate where we waited uh
and we wait on the total frame time
which is a good idea however what I
noticed is we don't track uh that fra we
don't uh snap that frame time uh
basically this last counter thing we
don't snap this at the right place what
we want to do is immediately after uh we
do sort of that um that lock right at
that that time is actually when we want
to get that end counter because that is
actually the thing uh that we are
looking at for our total time it'll
still it'll still count because you have
to remember this is basically just a
watermark that we in insert somewhere in
our Loop and if we're waiting for our
Target seconds per frame we want to wait
uh on the entire time that it takes to
do everything up to this point and then
immediately after we want to snap
whatever that time was and count the
rest of the stuff towards the next
frame's time uh because otherwise we'll
wait till the target time then there'll
be a bunch of time afterwards when we're
doing stuff uh like doing our our sync
display and our buffer and all that sort
of stuff so this really needed to get
moved uh to here and we didn't do that
and we we saw that I remember I said we
need to look at that tomorrow we saw
that in the fact that these numbers were
wrong they were a little over 33 and
that amount that was over was exactly
that time that was taken up in here
because we were waiting till our Target
frame time which was 33 then still doing
some work without count um that would
count inside that that frame Benchmark
so I just wanted to fix that to get one
bug out of the way because I thought of
it last night after we finished I was
like oh we've got one bug in there
already um so I wanted to fix that uh
and see yeah and so you can kind of see
now as well um yeah that's fine uh
basically you can kind of see now that
that 33 is right on the money and that's
what I wanted I wanted us to be locked
at 33 frames a second and that's exactly
what I wanted uh now this assert we've
got an assert here that fires anytime we
miss our frame rate um and so that's you
know what you would expect if you switch
to another uh guy so that this is this
is kind of something that we're not
going to be able to uh to do anything
about certainly because when we do our
sleep we the operating system like I
said before when we do our sleep if
we're not the running application we're
not uh getting priority we might sleep
for a very long time so this is just an
assertion in debug mode to tell us when
we miss our frame rate so if we switch
apps it's going to happen because
windows will just see no particular
reason to to give us the resources we
need to always hit it so that's fine but
uh now we are basically running at 3
uh 33.33 milliseconds per frame exactly
as far as we can tell from our wall
clock time which is exactly what I
wanted so we know that that part's
working properly uh but um when I look
at our sound you can kind of see there's
some weird kind of gapping unless we've
got a bug in the way we're recording it
and you can kind of see what's happening
there if I pause uh this this uh like
let's say I just take a pause here right
um I don't know if I can get uh let's do
it this way I'm going to go ahead and
take this guy sort of over here so this
way we can run
um the app and then kind of stop the app
uh in the middle if that makes sense I
don't know if that'll actually how well
that'll actually work I kind of just
needed to um how can I do this how can I
do this I guess I'll just make it kind
of tiny this is why people often have
two monitors if they're doing a lot of
uh debugging work
okay no that's not what I wanted
so what I want to do is just stop it so
you can see it there we go so what you
can see is going on here is we're
getting nice sort of equispaced samples
most of the time but then sometimes we
get kind of these nasty uh hiccups where
it's totally not right at all you can
kind of see that there were two lines in
here and there were two lines in here
two lines in here no line there uh so
we're not getting a very stable read on
the audio pointer right that that that
when we're asking for where that is it
doesn't look like we're getting a very
stable read from it now I don't actually
know at the moment why that is it could
be that this sound card just doesn't
give us a very stable read uh back from
the frame buffer I honestly don't know
uh but what I can say is at least right
now we're getting back a very unstable
uh sort of piece of information from it
for that play cursor and I don't
actually know exactly why that is so
it's something to think about though uh
so what we want to do here is start to
sort of improve our situation uh what I
want to do is kind of try to do
something let's try to think about this
here I wonder if there's a way we can
ask for slightly more accurate time or
if that's the most accurate time we're
going to get because if that's if if you
think about it if that actually isn't
buggy uh right if that is not buggy at
all um excuse me then uh we're we're
kind of in a little bit of trouble to
try and get audio sync I mean if you
think about how inaccurate it would have
to be if that's where it actually is um
but so let's just take a look at that a
little bit a little bit here just to see
if we can increase that accuracy if
we're doing something stupid or you know
hopefully hopefully there's something
we're just missing so when we call this
get current position here uh let's just
take a look at the documentation for
that uh direct sound get current
position um just to see if there's
anything that we could be doing uh when
we create the buffer or anything like
that to make it be a little bit more
accurate I don't know if we can or not
but uh let's see let us see what it says
here the right cursor in is safe to
write blah blah blah we know all this uh
that is not going to help help us let's
take a look at the buffer creation stuff
uh just so we can kind of see set
frequency is not really going to help
none of this looks particularly
interesting but we can take a look at at
some of these things like the caps and
stuff and then I can also take a look at
this create sound buffer uh so we can
kind of take a look at whether there's
anything we can do inside the buffer
description to tell it that we kind of
need uh some better stuff so uh let's
see so we don't really know what
position notify exactly is I assumed
that was called back but maybe that
might have some uh bearing on it let's
see here she's new IND direct sound
let's let's take a look what some of
this stuff says because some of this may
be
relevant so in direct sound DirectX one
the play cursor was significantly ahead
of the actual playing sound on emulated
sound cards it was directly behind the
right cursor now if the appc can get a
more accurate play position if this flag
is not specified the old behavior is
preserved for compatibility so so you
know I'm just like I said going down on
a limb here let's just try some of these
and see if we can get that guy to be a
little smoother and hope that it's just
a little bit of something we're doing
wrong that's causing that and that it
doesn't have anything to do with the
actual uh platform which would be a lot
harder for us to work around so I'm
going to go ahead and set that in here I
believe uh it is well I guess it's only
on our secondary buffer that we care I'm
not sure uh I'm not sure if that's true
or not um but I believe it is let's see
uh let's see here directly if the blah
blah blah blah blah if this flag is not
sui the old note that this flag affects
only emulated sound cards direct sound
drivers present play cursor is accurate
for direct sound in all
versions well uh this probably isn't an
emulated sound card is the thing so
that's not a good that's not a good sign
for us but what are you going to do all
right uh we'll we'll try it anyway just
to see uh is there anything else on here
that might have a bearing on it primary
buffer no static no Focus no no Global
Focus none of this stuff none of this
stuff looks uh particularly useful yeah
well well we'll try we'll just we'll try
some things and see if we can get any
luck that definitely does not improve
anything uh let me also double check
that that's not the right cursor that we
don't have some kind of bug where we're
asking for them in the wrong order or
something stupid like that because that
could C certainly happen just want to
make
sure let's see here uh so back up a
little bit to get current position it is
the play cursor first the right cursor
second so we're doing that correctly and
not much we can say about that uh set
format the set format is not going to
have anything for us I don't think and
get caps well we can get a caps bits and
there is not a lot there we could see if
it has this but that's about it so I
don't know not looking great for our
hero what I will say is let's not
despair uh just quite yet um you know
it's sort of disparage e it's sort of
time to dispair a little bit to get get
our dispair on but what I'm going to do
is I'm going to do a win32 um uh time
marker or uh debug time marker I'm going
to go ahead and and um put something in
here that's got basically a play
cursor um play
cursor and a right cursor right like
that uh and I am just going to go ahead
and use that as what our array is so our
markers and our marker count and then I
will just sort of uh change this here to
that and so we can get uh win 32 debug
time marker this marker equals that so
at that point I can do play cursor that
way uh and that will be uh easy for us
to get out and that's good
um that should just be my count there we
go and then uh down in the other
function here we have to basically do uh
debug time
markers uh and debug time markers now
you can see what I'm doing here is
really very straightforward I had
something working where I was just
recording one value and I wanted to
record more than one value so I just
broke it into a struct again this is
this is that compress oriented
programming sort of style that I'm
talking about where just when you find
you need something just do the step that
gives you what you need and the code
sort of marches towards better uh over
time right it just gets a little cleaner
a little better a little more flexible
as you go uh and everything uh hopefully
works out for the best so these are
going to be our debug time markers uh
and that should be roughly it so uh
debug time marker index debug time
marker
and we want this to just be
that probably could have done this with
a search and replace a lot easier but
you know sometimes debug time markers
you just don't think about it and this
guy needs to be changed up here there we
go all right
uh no conversion you're right there is
no conversion uh but you know what I can
do uh win through to debug time marker
marker equals address of that so I can
just snap the address of that uh and
then what I'll actually do is I'll just
uh go ahead uh and get it directly into
this thing so there we go marker Arrow
play cursor Marco error right cursor and
now I've got both of them so with both
of them uh I can now also go ahead and
uh and draw them both if I want to and
see how those look as well so I'm going
to go ahead and do that I'll just lean
on our vertical line draw again and so
basically what I'll do here is just say
Okay um let's go ahead and pull that out
as well into just a little guy that does
this exact thing that uh and this will
be uh wi 3 to draw sound buffer marker
or something like this uh and that will
take a substantively the exact same
stuff like so uh it will just take the
coefficient here uh that we had and it
will just do exactly this stuff so uh
this is where local functions would be
really nice by the way um you know
features that sort of get added to the
language over time stuff that you would
want that is definitely one of them all
right uh so all we really need to do
here is just pass this the things that
it doesn't have uh which is the C uh and
the pad X the top and the bottom so uh I
will go ahead and call that and I'll
call it on both things like so all right
uh so Global back buffer um sound I
don't know why we're still calling This
Global back buffer by the way that's
kind of absurd it should just be back
buffer in here because it doesn't
actually care that it's using the global
one it's not Global anymore it's just
using one that's passed in so we'll get
that out there and we'll do this so
there we go pad X top
and bottom like so there we go all right
uh so that's all good now we just need
to pass two different values to it uh
which is basically going to be uh this
thing right here so this is our value
that we actually want to draw that's
coming in and I will just pass a
different thing I'll pass the play
cursor uh and maybe the color here and
I'll pass uh the right cursor and a
different color here let's say uh
something like that you know and uh this
might be a good time to turn off our
gradient to say the least um but you
know it's so pretty sometimes it's hard
to part with it certainly uh so we'll do
that and we'll get a color in here so we
can do them two different colors so I'm
just going to pass the right cursor and
the play cursor so I can see the two of
them as well so let's go ahead and fix
that buffer
and back
buffer go and that should be it I should
be seeing the red ones as well
here
yeah it's just not looking it's not
looking good for our hero is
it yeah yeah I don't know that's that's
not uh that's not what you want to see
certainly in your life I mean you can
kind of see if I pause this guy
um at any particular point in the
execution here uh you can kind of see
what's going on there there's just a
really even though we've got some
measure of verification that we're
always updating ourselves at basically
the right amount of time we're we're
definitely getting just a really bad uh
kind of readback from the sound card
here that's that sort of seems pretty
unreliable to me I don't know hopefully
maybe there's we're still doing
something uh wrong but you can see why
I'm just thinking getting in any kind of
tight audio sync when you've got that
much variability is really just not
probably something that's going to be on
the table uh if that makes sense but
what can you do uh of course we're not
really calling it right at the moment uh
so maybe maybe let's go and actually do
the work of what we're going to do today
uh what I was hoping would be enough
today but you know with that with with
looking at how bad that is in terms of
it stuff it's unclear that we're going
to get anything in terms of sound sync
but uh maybe it's just because we're
calling it sloppily at the moment maybe
the fact that we're doing the lock in a
bad way is causing the hiccup I don't
know um or maybe we've got something
else stupid going on so for now I won't
despair quite yet um it was a little
despairing to see it but you know maybe
maybe um maybe we can UND
despair so uh what we want to do here is
since we kind of know roughly what our
frame sync is going to be uh in fact we
can sort of look uh back at the
beginning here and we can see uh what
our what our frame situation looks like
it's pretty consistent we always are
actually getting that 33 frames a second
that we want to pretty much across the
board when our app is not getting
interrupted or anything we're getting a
pretty good uh read on that it seems
like so if that's always uh getting 33
milliseconds of frame round trip time
then basically what we should be able to
do at the very least is just write 33 uh
we should be able to sort of like keep
ourselves that far ahead uh in the sound
buffer uh and that should should be
sufficient for our purposes so so
basically when we go to actually write
the sound out um which is right here
when we actually go to write the sound
out we should be able to just do it uh
by writing however much ahead our actual
frame time is and and using that so
basically
um
basically what we want to do is we want
to do something along the lines of this
so we kind of want to go here and say
all right
um we're going to do our game update and
render uh and then we're going to go
ahead and we're going to uh right into
the location that we think the sound
will be at uh at that time uh well yeah
yeah there's couple different ways we
could do this let's think about this
this is why I said this was going to be
very hairy and complicated I think I
said it originally
um we may have to eat up some Q&A time
on this one because it's going to be
pretty hairy all right so the problem
that we have is basically we know we
have to write from the last position
that we wrote to right uh because our
Sound Stream has to be continuous uh and
so basically what we're doing here is
we're sort of doing exactly that we're
passing the btes to right uh and we're
passing the samples here uh so what
we're trying to figure out here is how
far ahead of the of the current play
cursor we should be writing so we're
doing the play cursor uh plus whatever
our latency is now we're expecting the
play cursor right from wherever it was
we basically want to use the play cursor
plus 33 milliseconds we want to use the
play cursor that we sampled back when we
flipped the previous frame and we want
to add our frame latency into that
effectively right uh so what we want to
do is we want to we want to actually go
and I guess this is no this makes this
not really debug anymore uh we actually
want to go ahead and do uh this this
cursor access uh we want to do that
access actually um back here right if
that makes any sense so what we want to
do is say okay uh let's go ahead and
take that
sample at that time uh we'll basically
say all right uh when we actually grab
this we're also this is no longer no no
five minute warning no wait this is
selectable text is that actually true no
no it's I I I thought for a minute it
was like letting me select this which is
kind of hilarious it's actually talking
about emac so that's fine okay uh
anyway uh so what I got to do here or
what I'm going to do here is I'm going
to say when we do our flip we're going
to look at whatever the sound card said
it was uh at that time so we're already
doing that so now this is no longer
debug code basically uh this is actually
going to be uh real code so we're going
to uh access that play cursor and the
right cursor and we're then going to
record them for debug purposes in debug
builds so that we can draw them uh but
we're actually going to always also have
them as well uh if that makes sense so
we're going to go ahead and say that
there is a play cursor and a right
cursor D Rod that's
good I'm going to get them both
here there we go and I will uh actually
store them assuming that they worked uh
we'll have to handle it uh with the
sound is valid thing here otherwise the
sound is not valid
here there we go uh and then I will
simply set last play cursor equal to
play cursor and so we will actually have
some understanding of where the play
cursor is now we're going to have to
handle startup specially uh
dword play cursor there we go uh to do
Casey handle startup
specially uh but then once we get
through here uh once and and our sound
is valid where is our sound sound is
valid uh our sound is valid also needs
to be uh stored here as well okay so our
our startup's going to be totally messed
up there's no question about that uh but
I'm just trying to get the actual frame
to frame update working properly first
so uh when I come in here I no longer
need to do this uh basically all we need
to do is ask whether the sound is valid
or not and assuming the sound is valid
then we do the computation uh using the
play cursor that we already have so in
here instead of using play cursor we
will use last play cursor there will be
no cursor query here and we'll do our
computation off of that now when we get
that uh we will then ask to write
essentially however far ahead we want
for our latency and that latency can be
the frame time plus some if we want to
add additional buffer in there uh so
whatever the latency sample count
actually comes out to be let's take a
look at how we're Computing that right
now it looks like we're doing a 15 of a
second uh so maybe what we'll do here is
actually shorten that down for now to
actually be one frames worth so that
would be basically uh the samples per
second uh divided by the frame rate
update Hertz uh and then if we wanted to
move it back to uh to be two frames
worth so it's always writing an extra
frame ahead we can do that for now by
putting in the two uh right so we can
put like frames of audio latency
something like that
we can actually say that that's a thing
that we have right so we have that uh so
let's take a look at that for a second
here I think that's a little more sane
of course it's not really going to fix
any of our problems that we had but I
just wanted to get that in there uh
first of course the fact that I hear no
sound right now is not a good sign um
but looking
at uh looking at it it it does appear to
be a little
more stationary and
stable Maybe
maybe I don't know about that is that
more stable sir does look more stable to
me uh those are not double lines they're
just we're using stretch blit so
remember it's going to kind of stretch
our Graphics a little bit so it looks
that's looking better to me that is
looking better I feel like wouldn't you
say I don't know it looks it looks a
little more stable to me it's still a
little variable more variable than I'd
like but that looks more stable so maybe
if we're very lucky it was just the fact
that we were locking the buffer kind of
wonky uh that was causing it to be
errant and I'm really crossing my
fingers that that's what it is and not
just the fact that the sound card is
going to be really inaccurate on this
machine um wouldn't surprise me because
it's one of those weird real Tech
embedded like 5-cent chips or
whatever but hey the reality is that's
what's in a lot of computers so you know
we got to work on that stuff we can't
have some kind of gourmet sound card all
the time uh that's not on the table all
right so sound is valid
let's take a look at what goes on with
sound is valid uh basically we've got
sound is valid being set to True when we
can get the play cursor and sound is
valid equal to false when we can't uh so
if that's equal to true I'm not sure
exactly why we were having a problem
here uh we were using last play cursor
uh to Target it uh are we for some
reason not oh we yeah that's good we
dropped that succeeded line we got to
love that succeeded it always it always
comes and gets you uh I think it
succeeded let me double check again I
forgot what that what that actually was
so basically that was get current
position uh and return values it's DSO
so no I guess I don't use succeeded I
use
DS equals DS okay there we go so that
should turn our sound back on there we
go so at least our sound is back on now
but we're still getting scratchy so
we're still got a bug
um and and it's still it looks a little
gappy I don't know we still got a bug
though you can hear that scratching this
there's no real reason for it uh so
we're doing something stupid I'm just
not exactly sure what so let's step
through and see what's going on here
because I kind of did that a little bit
hastily it does say the Q&A begins now
but I think I'm going to go through the
Q&A time a little bit just so I can kind
of finish debugging at least the step
that we were on because I don't want to
uh sort of lose the mental state if you
will of what the changes that we were
trying to make because it's nice to be
able to make a single change and then
kind of like put it down and say okay uh
we're basically done so uh I'm going to
remove this to-do because that is
exactly what we're doing here so
assuming the sound is valid we're going
to take a look here and look at where we
were in The Sound output um and we are
going to map that into our sound buffer
we're going to say that and that's just
where we're going to write to right um
then we're going to take wherever that
last play cursor is so that's where
wherever we flipped the last frame we're
going to take a look at where that is
we're going to advance um however many
samples of latency we want we're going
to advance there times the bytes per
sample uh and then we're going to
basically say that is the location that
we want we're going to map that uh
essentially into the buffer size as well
so we're modding both these by the
buffer size to make sure they both stay
in uh the buffer so assuming that the
bite to lock is greater than the target
cursor
um that assumes that it wraps I guess
it's just assuming that it wrapped then
the btes to is right is the whole size
minus whatever the bite to lock is so
this this looks a little hairy to me
actually let's Okay so this
is we're just going to say we're going
to check that next uh but I want to take
a look at that so all right so we'll get
rid of this now because we're actually
debugging that uh so we make the sound
buffer we basically say how many samples
we're going to write and that's however
much we computed in here so this guy is
controlling everything this is basically
uh compute how much sound to write and
where right okay uh so we we have that
uh I would like to know where does where
does running sample index where does
that get updated so that gets updated in
here so basically our our our fill sound
buffer will advance that and
it's updating it correctly so that's
good okay uh so so we're going to lock
that we're going to figure out what's
going on there uh we'll look at that
that's we're going to check a little
more detail later uh so we call the game
update and render and that actually gets
our sound output for the sample the
number of samples that we thought we
wanted
um which is basically however many bytes
there are divided by the byes for sample
that's how many samples we're going to
write uh so that's fine and then we're
going to check if the sound is valid
meaning if this if the last time we
looked at the position it actually was
able to give it back to us we are going
to go ahead and fill the sound buffer uh
at that point with whatever came back
from the game uh we're then going to
sleep we're just going to go ahead and
wait and let it C let it catch up to
where that should roughly have been um
and that's fine we're then going to go
ahead and do the seconds elapsed and
then once we actually do the flip we're
going to look at where the play cursor
was so that doesn't look totally stupid
to me there's nothing obviously dumb
about it uh but of course there's a lot
of math in there and it does seem like
it's like a little finicky one thing we
could do um and maybe this is a good
idea is to sort of encapsulate some more
of this math we're doing a lot of this
math by hand here and there's a lot of
possibilities for error like when stuff
is in samples versus in bytes and stuff
and it's kind of uh the onus is on you
when you write each individual equation
to do it right so it could be that we
should go ahead and encapsulate that uh
so we have a handle that works in
samples or something like that that we
just use and we know that it gets mapped
down to bytes properly something like
this um we could think about that but
for now I want to take a look at this so
basically let's see what happens the
first time through here we have some
Target cursor right the first time
through here sound isn't going to be
valid anyway the next time through we're
going to have a location uh and we're
going to have a place a running sample
index set to zero so we're going to
write we're going to do an invalid write
the first time through which is why I
said we have to handle startup specially
because we're going to write from the
beginning of buffer to where we should
write but really what we should do is
only write from like the the right
cursor up to there so really there's a
thing that's like if it's the first time
you know uh it should use the right
cursor so like something like this to do
uh if first time through right from
right cursor kind of a thing um or just
if it's the first time through in fact
you know we can we might as well just do
this so all you actually have to do is
the running sample index the first time
sound uh becomes valid again basically
we would say if uh the sound was if
sound was not valid right if the sound
was not valid so we we lost where we
were playing somehow which would be on
Startup or at some other time when the
buffer went haywire or some weird thing
which probably should never happen uh
but let's say it did uh then that
running sample index uh where we need to
write should just be the right cursor
right it should be the right cursor like
where we should write to um and we just
need to map that into samples so in
order to do that we just have to divide
uh by the samples uh the bytes for
sample right that's that's really all we
have to do so we're just going to do
that um and and so that actually at
least will make it um be be more correct
in theory on Startup I think uh we'll
have to well again we'll have to
actually debug that so I think that's
right on Startup now uh as well let's go
ahead and look there take take a look at
that
special handle startup I said There It
Is specially uh because now we're
actually handling that so we've got it
bugs but we are actually at least trying
so okay what I'd like to do I guess is
take a quick look at what actually
happens when we come in here uh but I
want to check out this equation by
inspection first uh just so I can see
what's wrong with it so anyway uh okay
we've got our to lock right and we've
got our Target cursor so if the bite to
lock is ahead of the target cursor uh
then that basically means uh I guess
that we're wrapping so we're kind of
going to have to write all the way
around the SEC the the buffer uh if that
makes sense so our bytes to right at
that point are equal to however much we
have left in the buffer that seems right
uh plus however far we need to go to get
to the Target cursor that seems correct
otherwise um so in the other case if
they were
equal uh what would btes to right be
btes to right would just be nothing and
that seems right because if they're if
they're the same we wouldn't need to
write anything and in the other case
where the tar Chris's head of bites a
lock we just need to go that far right
uh so that does seem that does seem
about right uh so what I would like to
do now I guess is just take a look at
what happens uh the first time through
uh and you know what we could do as well
um is we could do an output debug string
here to kind of give us just a look at
what's going on uh just periodically
right we could do a thing where we
basically say uh okay uh let's go
ahead here and just do a
little uh you do it this way let's just
do a a write that's just basically going
to tell us where we wrote to where the
play cursor was that sort of stuff uh so
let's just do something like this this
where we say uh the play cursor whatever
it was um the bite to lock uh and uh the
target cursor uh and the bytes to write
so that just so we can have a little
running log again just a sanity check uh
and before and then the next step would
be obviously to to um to actually go
ahead and draw these out uh a little bit
better so we can see why exactly we're
getting that skipping because I'm I can
draw these I could draw these writes in
as well uh so byes to
write um let's see here Target cursor B
to WR
bite to lock there we go uh so now we'd
also get a log of our audio uh so we can
just take a look at it here and kind of
see what's going on uh so looking at
this right uh this is actually kind of
roughly what we would expect from a hard
whereare that wasn't reporting itself
very granular right uh we're basically
getting a bite to write value that stays
locked at some very close values uh so
they're either it's either writing this
much or it's writing this much uh and so
that's exactly what we' expect for
something that updates at a you know a
non- cycle GL granularity um so that
seems totally reasonable um it also kind
of tells us wow that the the granularity
is not particularly good if that's
actually the case um and we could
actually see I guess what the
granularity was if we wanted to uh one
thing that we could do which would be
kind of fun I suppose is just to sit in
a locked Loop and see how often that uh
that updates that would actually tell us
I guess exactly once we actually start
things uh once we actually start the uh
the direct sound buffer playing uh
wherever that is play there it is we
could sit in the locked Loop right here
uh and actually take a look at that in
fact I may actually suggest that that's
actually what we want to do so we can
see what our granularity is uh just
right off the bat so I'm going to go
ahead and do that so basically right
here uh I'm going to go ahead and do a
while loop that basically just locks us
up the app will never exit when I put
that this in here basically what I'm
going to do is I'm just going to take a
look um at at what that uh what that
play cursor and what that right cursor
are reporting um as we go so basically
I'm just going to do this call right
right right here in a locked Loop uh
that will do nothing other than it uh
and then I'm just going to print those
out so I'm going to print out play
cursor uh and right cursor as as bytes
so play cursor and right cursor and
that'll let us see how often they even
update at all like what the granularity
is yes thank you uh for telling me that
it is unreachable code um it certainly
is unreachable code uh I'm well aware of
that uh fine let's let's say while
Global running uh equals true are you
happy about that does that make you
happier thank you all
right uh so now oops got to have a
carriage return in there so now we
should be able to see um as we go did I
miss a carriage return in the other one
too no I didn't have it in there so now
we should be able to see what the
granularity here is here of the sound
cards reporting right uh this will
basically tell me how often it updates
because you can see basically it just
reports the same thing over and over and
over and over again and when it does go
up it goes up by a very specific value
so if I do this calculation right this
is in bytes remember this is printing
out in bytes uh so if I do this
calculation the sound card is giving me
back that position the previous position
it gave me back was that one and that's
well
1920 uh first of all we know we are
running at four bytes per sample right
that is our bytes per sample two 16bit
values so I divide that by four and I
get back
480 uh so 480 samples should roughly be
uh so four 480 samples is my value I'm
going to write that down here so I don't
forget it 480 samples is the granularity
that I can hope to get back from this
thing uh and the number of samples per
second is that is 48,000 so assuming
that we're updating at 30 frames a
second uh that
480 should actually be three per frame
so it should be enough uh for what we're
trying to do to work uh that's above
Nyquist
certainly it feels like that should be
able to
work I have to think about this so it's
updating on forun Sample granularity uh
for each frame right we have 30 frames a
second so we have 1,600 samples in a
frame so 3200 samples is how many ahead
we would be writing we certainly
shouldn't be getting Skips from that uh
so we're definitely doing something
wrong uh I'm just not exactly sure what
it is but that's good to know I'm just
going to drop a little comment in here
uh next to this little while loop that
we just
made uh so basically I'm going put an if
zero around it so it doesn't compile but
then I'm going to put a little thing in
here that says note Casey uh this tests
the audio update frequency uh the or I
should say the play cursor uh right
cursor update frequency uh on the
handmade hero
machine it was for na0
samples right uh so there you go so 4
any samples was our latency all right so
moving back to where we were at before
we're getting our nasty audio skip uh
and why are we getting that uh so the
play cursor was here uh right our bite
to right was quite a bit ahead of that
and then the next time the play cursor
was here uh I guess we should also
probably be recording uh what the right
cursor was maybe we're not far enough
ahead of it uh that's a good question I
guess I'll double check that as well uh
because we don't know how far ahead that
right cursor normally is well actually
you know what uh we did CU I just
actually ran the thing that said that
but I'm going to add that into our thing
here so last play cursor I'm going to
put in the last right cursor as well or
actually not even the last one uh get
current position I'll actually just go
ahead and call that right before we do
our right uh and then print that out so
we can essentially see exactly where we
ended up writing to so basically what
I'm going to do here right is I'm just
going to say uh okay get that get that
current position right in
there uh and this should probably we
should probably put internal uh uh
builds around all of these things where
is the uh buildup at here handmade
internal this we're going to have to go
through and put that around a bunch of
stuff but anyway we're going to take a
look at that and say okay give us back
uh the play cursor and the right cursor
uh right at this time we're going to
ignore the play cursor for now but then
I'm actually going to go ahead and do
this print out down here uh so that what
I can do is say all right when we filled
that sound buffer
where did it actually think uh we were
so this was the play cursor this was the
last play cursor uh and then this is
what the play cursor and the right
cursor are now right so that we can just
see did we did we actually just miss our
timing or something are we writing are
we not giving it enough Headroom that
sort of thing I'm just trying to figure
out U what our problem is with the
skipping so I'm just trying to look at
where we are writing uh in the buffer
that makes sense so let's take a quick
look at
that all right uh so the last play
cursor was here by the time we query it
it's here so it has advanced one uh once
here is uh where the yeah so that's well
that's the numbers don't lie ladies and
gentlemen the numbers do not lie
basically the right cursor is just hella
ahead uh of of uh of that play cursor so
it looks like it looks like um we're
pretty much going to have to increase
that audio latency it looks like the
audio latency just isn't going to be
enough
uh that's unfortunate that's a a lot of
audio latency if you think uh about how
far ahead that is
um gosh yeah that's that's kind of crazy
um but that looks like that looks like
the truth is that is that really right
um so so what's what is the Delta there
what is the what is the mandatory audio
latency basically the the lowest audio
latency we would ever hope to get uh
coming out of this coming out of direct
sound here uh what is it
5920 holy cow look at that look at that
value oh oh
man all right well all
right that's so that's the number of
samples right and that's like several
frames right so uh how much of a second
is that if I do the Divide
paste that's uh oops I did that wrong
let me do that one more time we need I
need something better than this
calculator for doing this stuff so
that's the number of of bytes uh so
divide by four that's the number of
samples uh and so basically 1440 so 1440
wow so it's actually gosh so it's
actually asking for 30 frames a second
ahead of latency just to begin with so
I'm going to have to be even more than
that yikes so I don't know I maybe I'm
misreading these numbers maybe it's just
you know like I said I'm it's it's
always a bit of a rush here when I'm
doing stuff on a live stream uh so it's
a little bit tough for me I will say
that but that that looks to me like
basically what's happening is we need
even more latency above what we were
already specifying I could be wrong
about that so we'll just go a little Hog
Wild here and see if that's true if I
say four frames of audio latency for
example what do I
get well that's scary people that is
scary well I'm glad stuck with it
because we know the piece of information
now that we needed to know which is that
basically we are talking about something
that's going to force us to write pretty
far ahead and we do have a very narrow
uh range there uh maybe we should look
we should probably look at the right
cursor first look at how far ahead it is
normally and adjust our our latency uh
to compensate for that
um but yeah there's not a lot more we're
going to be able to do it looks like two
frames of latency is just not quite
enough uh to make it work so we'll have
to yeah it's just not quite enough and
it catches up to
us all right
well not what I would have hoped for
that's a lot of latency that's a lot of
latency but uh that's just what we're
going to have to live with for now um
yeah that's just quite a bit that it's
basically mandating
there I uh I guess that'll be an
interesting thing when it comes time to
kind of tighten things up up for ship
maybe we Implement X audio and we see if
we get lower latency out of it um or we
hope that we do anyway um I don't know
uh but I would say that's about probably
it for now we're almost out of time I
would like to take 10 minutes of
questions if we can uh so I don't want
to go any longer certainly uh but we
would probably have to still tighten
this up a little bit tomorrow because I
kind of slammed all that in here and
there's a bunch of loose ends uh like
all these printouts and stuff so we're
going to have to wrap all that stuff up
as well so we're not really done with
what we wanted to do today we're pretty
darn close though uh but we're not quite
done uh because what I want to do here
is actually draw where we're writing to
so that we can look a little bit more at
what's going on so I'm going to say um
to do draw where we're writing our sound
because that's where I'd hope to get to
I'd hope to get it playing smoothly and
drawing it out so we can see um and so
we'll have to do that tomorrow which
means we might spill over into Monday or
maybe we sneak in a secret week week end
stream you know you can you can work
over time once in a while uh so we'll
see all right so uh with that stated
let's actually still do uh 10 minutes of
questions if you could please uh make
sure that your question includes seator
in it somewhere uh so that I will see it
I have a little thing that looks for
seor so that it cuts out talk between
people uh and basically uh if you could
please keep the questions to things we
did tonight or in a previous night uh
let's not talk about stuff we're going
to do in the game later because we will
do that when when we actually get there
and and we've obviously got tons of
stuff uh that we've already done so far
so let's keep the questions to
that all right let's
see are you set up to use ASI sound
drivers uh I'm not set up to do anything
special on this machine it's as far as I
know anyway at least I don't think so
it's just a def default install of a
default sound card uh so you know I had
hoped that you'd think that by the time
you get to Windows 7 right um You would
have mandated low audio latency to
people and you'd have like the pipe out
to the card would be good and whatever
but you
know it still requires all this special
F finesse I guess to do that sort of
stuff and or maybe they don't support
direct sound properly anymore and so if
we switch to X audio or something it
would I don't know we'll we find that
out down the line but yeah it's kind of
sad it should just work right I mean
there's no reason why this sort of thing
shouldn't just work uh so it's it's kind
of
unfortunate uh is your audio pointer
code calculating independently of the
variable fixed visual frames per second
uh yes essentially it is uh so basically
I have those two decoupled at the moment
basically what's happening is the audio
is just looking so the reason that I
have to do that is because the audio
clock is not guaranteed to synchronize
with the computer's clock right there's
no reason why the audio output clock has
to actually match the wall clock they
could diverge and if they diverge even
by a little bit then over time that
could lead to a big error uh that would
cause our audio to be writing to the
wrong place
right so what I need to do is I manage
my own frame rate here uh right I manage
my own uh video frame rate and then what
I do is I just look at where the sound
output is when we flip and I go okay
that's where we were when we flipped so
ideally we want to write uh to a
particular frame boundary we need to
look and frames in the future and write
to where a frame boundary will be in the
future that is the earliest frame
boundary we could write to right uh that
that is p the latency of that past the
audio latency of the sound card now we
could go a little further of this and
write
just only however much the audio latency
of the soundcard was and not truncate to
a frame boundary but that would
basically pass that burden onto the game
code to have to think about its audio
output being uncentered from a
frame should we do that should we not do
that I don't know I
mean I think you kind of want to
optimize more for the well-working
hardware case where stuff goes out the
HTMI kind of more synchronized and maybe
you know penalize the OS in some sense
for being crappy uh about that sync so I
don't know I'm disinclined to complicate
the game code in the service of this uh
but you know it's again it all depends
on what your aim is if you want to get
that extra you know millisecond or two
of latency out uh because you're an
audio game like for example a beat
matching game you make different
trade-offs and so I'm certainly not
going to say that one way is right or
one way is wrong because that's totally
not true uh but I think for this game
I'd say let's keep it on frame
boundaries and that's
that what kind what sort of problems can
high audio latency introduce well they
don't really introduce problems per se
they just make the experience feel a
little less tight you know ideally I'd
like one frame of audio latency so that
basically the visuals are almost exactly
in sync with the audio um I mean perfect
in in best of all possible worlds
exactly synced right um but that's not I
guess realistic uh in this particular
case now if we wanted to we could trade
visual latency for audio latency right
the way that we' do that is we'd render
frames and save them we'd buffer them up
right uh so we'd render like three
frames and we'd wait to flip the first
frame until we knew the audio had caught
up right and so we'd always sort of be
flipping behind where we knew the audio
was but that would introduce control lag
into the video and that seems like a
really bad trade-off uh so we don't want
to do that right uh so we're kind of at
a situation where we don't have any
choice but to take the audio lag because
that's just what what's going to happen
and what that means is that you know you
push the button and ideally you know if
you shoot or something you want the shot
sound to happen exactly as you push the
button uh and audio latency the higher
the audio latency the more lag there is
between when you push that button and
when you hear the result now
people are actually very forgiving about
this sort of thing they sort of
interpret things as
happening they interpret sounds as
happening synchronized to events even if
they aren't so if they see a shot and
they hear a shot sound even if they're
very far apart people actually think
they're happening at the same time so as
long as your game doesn't rely on them
hearing the sound and reacting
immediately to it like a beat matching
game does um you're probably actually
okay but even though the brain accounts
for it I still do feel uh and you know
this is subjective certainly but I still
do feel that narrowing that audio
latency does make it feel nicer to play
like taking some of that slop out just
it feels more visceral when your brain
is doing less of that correlation you
kind of are sort of aware of it when it
gets above a certain threshold now where
is that threshold you know that
threshold may be like 100 milliseconds
for a lot of people right which we are
well within um
but uh you know if that if that's at 30
milliseconds for most people let's say
then we are not even close uh we are
going to sound a little laggy to them
and so that's why it's just
disappointing I was hoping that the
hardware to Windows to Hardware pipeline
would have been better there it
isn't could you use that Anonymous Union
struct trick to access the members of
bitmap info header structure more easily
uh not really because there's nothing
you can really do um so so what the
person was asking was we basically have
this and the question was if we want to
reach in here and access something
inside the info uh could I use the
anonymous trick I did I I hopefully you
remember here I use that Anonymous
struct trick uh out in here uh to
basically push these names up into this
struct even though they're kind of in an
interior structure and the answer is not
really uh basically in order to do that
I would have to do something like this
right um I would have to basically make
this a descendant of it uh you can't
insert to the best of my knowledge
anyway you can't insert a struct
anonymously into another struct in
standard C I think there's an extension
that lets you do it um but I don't know
how well supported that extension
is so I'm sorry I guess I I don't know
of any way to do it no but there might
be well I should say I am 100% positive
there is an extension that can do it but
I don't know which compilers support it
whether there is a standard way to do it
that's supported across many compilers
that I don't
know uh let's
see how do you find the lowle sound
libraries to work with you choose direct
sound how did you make a meaningful
choice of that uh over audio or
something else uh the reason is because
uh it's the only thing that was that's
supported by default besides waveout on
XP as far as I know um I can look and
see whether there's another one that's
supported by default on XP um but I
wanted something again XP was our
compatibility Target we ran on it
already and everything worked just fine
uh and I wanted to make sure that that
continued to be the case
so I'm disinclined to switch to
something else at least for the
Prototype layer what we will do perhaps
in future ones is we will check to see
if x audio is there and try it now I
think one thing that I would point out
is I
suspect it would not surprise me in the
least to find that the latency is no
better with X audio so I know a lot of
people are always excited about like oh
oh yeah the latency is just bad because
you're using direct sound but they don't
actually know because they probably have
never tested it on this particular card
or whatever and so a lot of times people
get excited about something like you
should be using this API or you should
be using that API but that doesn't
actually come from experience and
they're just kind of speculating right
and so what I would emphasize here is we
don't actually even know if that will
improve things we will test later
whether that will improve our audio
latency but it's entirely possible that
this machine's audio latency just is
what that is and we're not going to get
any better uh so we'll have to actually
see in practice if that's the case so I
wouldn't get too excited about X audio
or wdm or any of the other Technologies
because it may be that they're all
roughly the same latency and it's the
sound chip that is actually causing the
latency
uh and its driver is just latent right
and that could very well be the case so
I would hold off on that kind of
speculation until we actually have some
data because otherwise it's just pure
guesswork suggesting that some or
another API uh will be
better um let's
see uh
let's see
here I'm not
seeing any other
questions uh that are about the audio
stuff uh let's see okay here's some yeah
sorry okay I missed this part right here
uh I don't understand what the what this
means someone said the sound is looped
begin Loop is at end Loop causing mega
loop simply space the code and this will
help I don't think I understand
that uh so you may have to repost that
um direct sound docs say don't write
before write cursor why are we safe
ignoring it suggestion don't overlap
play and WR vertical lines use half
screen for each that is a good
suggestion by the way um well we're not
really probably going to ignore the
right cursor like I said we kind of we
will probably use it in the future but
uh what you have to understand is the
right cursor actually isn't relevant to
us the right cursor is just something
that says don't write before this now
what we actually care about is where the
play cursor is right um and since the
the play cursor and the right cursor are
actually technically usually locked but
they're not really it's under no
obligation to lock them so what we want
to do is look at the play cursor and say
ideally what we want to do is write this
far in front of the play cursor right so
all we really want to do with the right
cursor is just add a little bit of code
that says make sure if for some reason
the right cursor is actually further out
than that uh by on average like we'll
look at where the right cursor how far
apart the right curs blor are on average
however far the right cursor is away if
that is more than what our expected
latency writing is then change our
expected L latency writing to
encapsulate that but we don't actually
want to use the right cursor because the
right cursor is actually irrelevant it's
just something that says says your
latency better be more than this but it
doesn't actually help us it doesn't
actually give us information about where
the sound is playing which is what we
actually care about for synchronization
if that makes
sense do you think splitting related
functionality like the sound into their
own files would make it easier to
conceptualize and debug uh not really uh
in fact it would probably make it worse
uh the reason I say that is because if
you take look at what happens in these
Loops they tend to get very interrelated
very quickly uh so for example we know
that we need to take um our our sound
check we need our sound check to happen
right when the flip happens and so this
is like coupled code here and if I was
to pull all this out into other code
that wouldn't be true anymore now if we
want to put it in a separate file and
make calls a bunch of calls in here then
that's fine but I'm not sure that
actually buys us very much it might
actually make it harder to read because
you have to guess what that function is
doing uh so no I don't think it would
improve it very much pulling it out into
a separate file I think that would just
make more work but I'm not
sure it's kind of personal preference so
if you want to put in a separate file
that's you know that's obviously up to
you if we use the play cursor as offset
could we not overwrite previously
written audio data uh well again I maybe
I need to draw a diagram because I this
seems to be uh confusing people so I'm
just going to go ahead and and draw draw
it uh one more time uh just so we can
kind of uh so that we can kind of get a
feel for it here um I don't know what
I'm going to use to draw it uh I guess I
could use smooth draw again but I think
I'm just going to go for the good old
Microsoft Paint uh painting tool of
Champions uh so
anyway just to be 100% clear about
what's happening here uh we're going to
get something uh well okay uh let's do
our frame ticks again so here's our
frame ticks these are happening at 30
frames a second second right uh so
basically each one of these is going to
be 33 milliseconds approximately right
33.3 33 bar so what happens is we're
going to query direct sound and it's
going to give us back something that
looks uh like this it's going to give us
back something that says the play cursor
is here and the right cursor is here
right and we now know that the
difference between these actually itself
is like 33 milliseconds if I remember
correctly right that's what we
computed uh so given that this is true
right um excuse
me what we want to know is we want to
know wherever the play cursor is right
we want to know where we can safely
write
to that's a frame you know where what
what frame boundary we can start writing
our audio to uh where is that in our
um how should I explain this which of
these frame boundaries can we safely
write to such that the right cursor if
you will uh won't catch up to there by
the time we actually output it uh and we
want it to be as close as possible to
the fact that when we actually do the
the page flip the play cursor will hit
that when we do the the page flip now
what we've basically determined is that
that's impossible because our frame rate
is actually roughly the same as our
audio latency so we're basically in a
really bad position um where we can't it
would just be cutting it too close uh to
try and do it so we actually need uh
three frames of latency to make this
work and the reason for that is that
since these this is about one frame uh
ahead right the right cursor is about
one frame ahead when we did our testing
what that means is that wherever the
play cursor is we know we probably can't
write we know we definitely can't write
to this because it's already behind the
play cursor and we know that we probably
can't write to this uh because given the
granularity of how this is being updated
we don't even know exactly the right
cursor could be anywhere really in
practice we're we're in we're in a lot
of trouble we don't actually know what's
going on with a lot of these things
because they're moving as we go uh so
really we have to Target basically one
frame ahead of the next frame that it
could be and that's where the three
comes from so we're on this Frame right
we have to skip this one we have to skip
this one probably unless we hit it dead
on and so we got to always write to this
one and that's where we come up with our
computation so the answer is can we
ignore the right cursor no we have to
look at that Delta there and find out
what it is and make sure that whatever
our frame latency is it's above that
value right but we don't actually care
where the right cursor is ever it
doesn't matter what we care is how far
it is from the play cursor we care about
this Delta right um because we're trying
to synchronize with this we're not
trying to synchronize with this we don't
care when the right cursor hit something
we care when the play cursor hits
something uh and that's that's about it
um so really it seems like this is
stupid when I'm saying it and that's
because this audio card is so latent but
imagine what would happen if this audio
card was better imagine what would
happen if when we queried it it looked
more like this right so here's the
difference right so here's the play
cursor here's the right cursor and now
you're saying well let's synchronize
using that well that's stupid because
what's going to happen is now you've
just introduced that much audio latency
uh on your frame boundary cuz you're
going to synchronize with when this
thing hits that thing and that's wrong
because this is actually the playback so
on a good card you would be very much
better off uh syncing with the play
cursor because it's going to be very low
latency and that is the thing you're
trying to sync with so you're only
checking this you're only checking this
Delta here to figure out uh what your
safety margin is on a bad card well it's
it's already totally latent anyway so I
actually don't mind the fact that we're
a little more latent like let's say
we're you know we're a little we're
we're you know an extra 10 milliseconds
latent when the thing was already 33
milliseconds latent isn't as big of a
deal to me uh necessarily like I said we
could be a little more proactive about
that and cut that down so that we
wouldn't have that by allowing the game
to write on non-frame boundaries uh but
I don't know I just don't know if I feel
like that's a good tradeoff to make
there um we have to see so that's that's
currently what what I'm
thinking it looks like it might be the
case that just like you'd favor direct
sound over wave out in Windows XP you
should favor wasapi or wave out for
Vista 7 so we might need two backends
for Windows based on OS if you want to
support both yes and that's why I said
what we'll probably do is we'll look
we'll test at some point um audio or
we'll test whatever the very latest
thing was on Windows 7 we'll see if the
audio latency is any better if it isn't
then we'll be like okay this is just a
waste of time but if it is then we'll
just have a thing that says if we were
able to open X audio we'll use it if it
wasn't we
won't would rendering at 60 frames per
second instead of 30 frames per second
help with this latency problem not
really it does cut down the extra frame
latency uh by a little bit uh so the
total latency would go from an extra 33
milliseconds to an extra 16 milliseconds
potentially on the rounding so whichever
direction it rounds uh you're rounding
to a different uh granularity so you
helps a little bit but that's only
because I said that I wanted to keep it
frame synchronized for audio if we
decided to desynchronize it and allow
the app to basically be writing to some
non-frame centered location which might
be a better decision you know as I'm
saying it more and more I'm thinking
maybe we should just allow that uh
because it doesn't really matter the
game doesn't really have to know the
game could think it was frame
synchronized and really all it's doing
is cutting down that latency a little
bit um so it's probably a better thing
to do anyway uh but at the moment we're
not actually doing that but yeah so if
we switch to that then it wouldn't
change at all uh the frame rate would be
irrelevant could you change latency
values based on detecting the sound card
settings yes and that is what we will do
uh based on the right cursor so tomorrow
we'll take a look at that right cursor
and the right cursor will determine uh
our our sound our sound granularity
basically is it possible that OBS is
affecting the audio latency that's a
very good point uh yes it is very very
possible um I had not thought of that
but you're totally right it could be
that that uh the fact that I'm
broadcasting this is what's causing that
that could very well be I had not
thought of that it's a very good point
um we'll have to run this uh with after
the stream's over I'll have to run it
and see to see if it's
different let's see
here all right I think that's it so I'm
going to set up some sados for tomorrow
just so we know what's going on here uh
so the first thing I'm going to say is
maybe we should just go ahead and run
non-frame locked um so I'm going to say
to do Casey uh let's think about running
non-frame quanti for audio latency uh
first of
all uh so maybe that's just a better
idea and the other to do is just let's
use that right cursor uh to to compute
whatever the latency is so to do Casey
uh let's use the right cursor Delta from
the play cursor to uh adjust the target
audio latency uh so that will that will
kind of give us that information
all right okay well thank you very much
everyone for joining us uh we kind of
did accomplish what I wanted to
accomplish today we're just a little bit
behind and so we'll have to push it into
tomorrow a little bit which means we may
spill over into Monday maybe 21 days of
platform code instead of 20 uh you know
who's counting software is always late
uh that's the kind of the rule so if it
has to be that way it has to be that way
but thank you very much for joining me
uh as always if you would like a copy of
the source code to play around with at
home along with the series you can go to
handmad her.org and pre-order it using
this handy dandy little button here uh
you can also if you would like to get
more information and discuss the series
with people you can click on this news
and forums button and you can basically
uh get all sorts of stuff here there's a
schedule on the homepage so you can see
what's going on uh there's an episode
guide uh which basically has all the
episodes uh with extra annotation on
them so you can learn from them more
easily there's a coding resources page
which has ports that people have done
among other things so for example uh if
you want to run this on macosx there's a
Code there's information about that
there's a um Linux as well there's a
bunch of stuff on there uh there's a
forum where we can discuss stuff there's
all kinds of things uh so please take a
minute to check that out if you have
questions or if you want to um discuss
stuff in the series it's a great
resource for that uh I will be back here
tomorrow but it's a Friday so it'll be
in the morning as we always do our
Friday morning so it's 11:00 a.m.
tomorrow Pacific Standard Time hope to
see those of you there who can make it
uh if not again you can always check the
video archive on YouTube uh to get that
uh right it should be up pretty soon
after it plays if not you can always use
twitch also has it immediately after it
airs uh so either one of those is your
source for that thanks everyone for
joining me and I will go test that audio
latency with OBS off uh so we can see if
that really was uh one of the problems
or not okay uh have a a great Friday if
I don't see you tomorrow or and a great
weekend I suppose um we'll be back
Monday at 8:00 p.m. PST if you can't
make the Friday stream tomorrow at 11:
a.m. thanks everyone and I will see you
later